Sanjeev Narasimhan

3 646-874-4594 **S** sn3007@columbia.edu **III** https://www.linkedin.com/in/sanjeevnarasimhan/ **○** sanjeevnara7

EDUCATION

Columbia University New York, USA

M.S. Computer Science, Machine Learning Research Specialization GPA: 3.97/4.00

May 2024

Birla Institute of Technology and Science Pilani

B.E. Computer Science GPA: **9.85/10** (3.97/4.00) Academic Merit Scholarship, Distinction Graduate

Pilani, India Jul 2020

SUMMARY

MS Graduate in Computer Science with research and practical development expertise in applied machine learning, specializing in computer vision problems. Focus areas include high-accuracy object detection and tracking for smart streetscapes and ML applications in surgery. Over 2 years of experience as an ML Researcher, and over 2 years as a Software Engineer with strong backend engineering and design skills. Seeking opportunities in Applied Machine Learning within the industry.

EXPERIENCE

Northwell Health New York, USA

Visiting Research Scientist - Applications of AI in Robot-Assisted Surgery

Jun 2024 – Present

- Developed a multimodal LLM evaluation system using Gemini 1.5 Pro to identify phases in robotic surgical videos, achieving up to 80% accuracy. Collaborated with researchers from Google to leverage Gemini with Google Cloud Vertex AI.
- Designed and trained custom video models on hernia surgery videos to perform real-time action recognition with up to 90% accuracy.
- Developed a computer vision system to assess surgical skill from robotic suturing videos using Video Transformer models and machine learning techniques (Random Forests, XGBoost), achieving 75% accuracy.
- Automated data preprocessing tasks using Python/C++ to enhance efficiency and accuracy of deep learning model training. Managed large-scale datasets efficiently, including data collection, cleaning, and annotation, ensuring high data quality for training and evaluation.

AIDL Lab, Columbia University (https://www.aidl.ee.columbia.edu)

New York, USA

Graduate Research Assistant - Video Based AI Models for Streetscape Applications

Jan 2023 - May 2024

- Developed and trained CNN models using Python and deep learning frameworks (PyTorch, TensorFlow) to accurately transform street-level views into bird's eye views with less than 10% error for automatic camera calibration.
- Curated and released a new object detection dataset named 'Constellation' with 13K+ high-elevation urban streetscape images. Provided state-of-the-art object detection model benchmarks as an open-source contribution, enabling robust small object detection research and identifying a 10% performance gap between aerial pedestrian and vehicle detection.
- Contributed to the analysis of selected COSMOS Testbed data https://cosmos-lab.org/experimentation/smart-city-intersections/

Summer Research Intern - Video Based AI Models for Streetscape Applications

Jun 2023 - Sep 2023

- Trained state-of-the-art object detection models including the most recent YOLO variants (YOLOv7, v8) using PyTorch. Customized the model architecture to achieve 95%+ accuracy for real-time vehicle/pedestrian detection.
- Applied LSTM-based trajectory forecasting models on object tracks to estimate trajectories up to 4 seconds ahead and detect potential vehicle-pedestrian collisions. Deployed the model to perform inference on an RTSP stream at a busy NYC intersection.

Deloitte Digital Bangalore, India

Software Engineer / Analyst

Oct 2020 - Jun 2022

- Built components on the Salesforce Cloud platform serving over a million end-users, supporting 100K+ average daily traffic with large volumes of data.
- 2+ years of experience with backend development with Java and database design with SQL, integrations (REST API), building front-end components (JavaScript/HTML/CSS).
- Led the project deployments using Git/Azure DevOps CI/CD pipelines for production releases.

PriceWaterhouse Coopers (PwC)

Dubai, UAE

Intern Software Engineer

Jan 2020 - Jul 2020

- Intern Software Developer, specializing in development on the Salesforce Platform. Gained experience with Java/Apex/SQL for backend development and handling bulk data.
- Implemented a Document Management System for a major government financial services entity and devised a centralized service system for 500+ qualifying companies.
- Engineered a backend solution for an educational institute serving over 50 thousand students, to assist in student enrollment and course administration.

Cadence (formerly Invecas Inc.)

Hyderabad, India

Intern Software Engineer

Jun 2018 - Aug 2018

Developed a full-stack web application with analytics dashboards to track project and employee performance, resulting in a 30% improvement in project management efficiency.

TEACHING

CS3 Streetscapes NSF Engineering Research Center (https://cs3-erc.org/)

New York, USA

Engineering Mentor

Jul 2024 - Aug 2024

- Mentored high-school students for the CS3 My Streetscape Summer Research Institute, an interdisciplinary education program on urban technology with the Center for Smart Streetscapes (CS3) at Columbia Engineering.
- Taught Machine Learning/Deep Learning concepts and familiarized students with end-to-end machine learning development, training and deployment.

Dept. of Electrical Engineering, Columbia University

New York, USA

Teaching Assistant - EECS E6691 Advanced Deep Learning

Jan 2024 – Jun 2024

• Head TA for seminar-style course, which covers advanced topics in deep learning including recent literature on state-of-the-art models. Responsibilities include teaching state-of-the art architectural and modeling concepts, preparation and grading of assignments/exams/projects and preparation and setup of in-class Kaggle competitions.

Teaching Assistant - ECBM E4040 Neural Networks & Deep Learning

Sep 2023 - Dec 2023

• Head TA for the delivery of graduate-level course which covers theoretical underpinnings, architectures and performance, and applications of neural networks. Responsibilities include grading of assignments/exams, setup of Google Cloud Linux Environments for the class to enable model training/development, and provide academic instruction to students in the classroom.

Athletics Department, Columbia University

New York, USA

NCAA Student Tutor

Jan 2023 – Jun 2023

• Instructed NCAA Student-Athletes at Columbia University in Data Structures and Algorithms using Java, adapting teaching methods to fit their unique schedules and learning needs.

PROJECTS

Stable Diffusion Inference Optimization

Dec 2023

- Benchmarked several state-of-the-art inference optimization techniques for Stable Diffusion v1.5 including quantization, token merging, distilled UNet/VAE and JIT compilation.
- Achieved up to 7x speedup in per-image generation time while maintaining high image quality by combining multiple optimization techniques.

Pass Receiver Prediction in Broadcast Soccer Clips

Apr 2023

- Developed a multi-stage system combining object detection, perspective transformation, clustering, and graph neural networks (GNNs) to predict optimal soccer player passes in broadcast clips.
- Attained 70% end-to-end accuracy on a custom dataset, highlighting the potential of the system to aid soccer professionals and broadcasters in gaining crucial information about the sport.

Neural Fashion Captioning using Transformers

Dec 2022

- Created an image captioning model for fashion data (DeepFashion Multimodal) using transformer networks to generate high-quality captions for finer attributes such as clothing fabric, jewelry, patterns, etc.
- Gained a 20% increase in caption quality (BLEU score) by pre-training the backbone to perform attribute classification.

PUBLICATIONS

- Turkcan, M.K.; Narasimhan, S. et al. "Constellation Dataset: Benchmarking High-Altitude Object Detection for an Urban Intersection." Preprint, (ArXiv 2024) /abs/2404.16944.
- Zang, C.; Turkcan, M.K.; Narasimhan, S. et al. Surgical Phase Recognition in Inguinal Hernia Repair—AI-Based Confirmatory Baseline and Exploration of Competitive Models. MDPI Bioengineering 2023, 10, 654.

SKILLS

Areas: Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Computer Vision, Data Science, Software Engineering

Languages: Python, Java, C, SQL, HTML5/CSS, JavaScript

Frameworks: PyTorch, Tensorflow, Keras, NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-Learn, CUDA, Android Studio, Bootstrap

Misc: Linux, HPC/Slurm, Google Cloud Platform (GCE), Git, GitHub, Docker, Azure DevOps, Agile Methodology, Salesforce